<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Pensieve - Stories</title><link href="https://al-faaz.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://al-faaz.github.io/feeds/stories.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://al-faaz.github.io/</id><updated>2019-09-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Coming to America</title><link href="https://al-faaz.github.io/stories/2019/09/05/coming-to-america" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Al Faaz</name></author><id>tag:al-faaz.github.io,2019-09-05:/stories/2019/09/05/coming-to-america</id><summary type="html">&lt;p style="text-indent: 0"&gt;Posterity is an irritating visitor. She breezes in, unannounced, smirks at the unkempt hair and the messy house, then, without even allowing time to fix anything, departs just as suddenly. It’s very annoying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To have something respectable to show Posterity for her next visit, I had, nineteen years ago …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p style="text-indent: 0"&gt;Posterity is an irritating visitor. She breezes in, unannounced, smirks at the unkempt hair and the messy house, then, without even allowing time to fix anything, departs just as suddenly. It’s very annoying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To have something respectable to show Posterity for her next visit, I had, nineteen years ago, captured my maiden travel experience from India to the USA in a short chronicle. Thanks to an email server crash, however, Posterity never got to see it. Finding that article since then has proven futile — none of the friends I’d sent it to had had the sense to save me a copy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, nineteen years later, I’m writing it all over again. I still remember most of the details, thanks to a brain that has an almost infinite capacity for the clutter of memories, thoughts and feelings one collects through life.
Here you go, Posterity, this is for you, whenever you come visiting again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Poonam Sagar Apartments, Andheri East, Bombay&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p style="text-indent: 0"&gt;If I were to graph my life, time versus the places I’ve lived, this point, today, would be a hole in that continuum. A cleft between yesterday and tomorrow. Yesterday I was here, fully and completely; tomorrow, I’ll have gone. Like someone waved a wand, and whoosh, I vanished. Like I was never even here. And never to return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Never&lt;/em&gt; is such an absolutist word, don’t you think? Such finality it carries. &lt;em&gt;Never&lt;/em&gt; will I ever be in this room again. This bed that I got out of, just today morning, &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; will I sleep in it again. Never again will I ride in that rickety lift, where you had to pull closed the two grill doors exactly right — or hear its whiny automated voice complain. And never again will I go to that seedy movie theatre with my colleagues-turned-friends for a late Friday night show. (And I shall definitely never have to run to catch the last bus from Victoria Terminus at midnight, then have to take a &lt;em&gt;taxi&lt;/em&gt; to reach my apartment, &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; apartment, at 2:00 in the morning!) It’s final, finished. After today, the things I used to do every day, I’ll never do them again. Not here anyway. Bombay will now exist entirely in memory, frozen in time, from where, slowly, imperceptibly, like wisps of fog in the sunshine, it will start to evanesce, day after forgotten day. Its sounds will become fainter, its colours dimmer — like photographs from long ago childhoods. And speaking of childhoods . . . at least I’ll get to spend some time in Delhi before I have to leave for the USA. &lt;em&gt;Which&lt;/em&gt; reminds me — I’d better hurry up and finish packing, or I’ll get an earful from Daddy for standing and daydreaming, while he does all the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daddy has come down from Delhi to help move all that stuff back. Well, not all that stuff. The mini refrigerator isn’t going. It now belongs to my roommate — along with that litre of milk, some vegetables, a bit of leftover food . . . and something that’s passed beyond recognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So long, little fridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m also bestowing on my roommate my portable stove with its one burner, and the tiny, black-and-white, pot-bellied TV with the rabbit-ear antennas. And of course, the metal rack that was my bookcase. Ah, my bookcase . . . guardian of the gifts of two years’ worth of biweekly pilgrimages to my favourite bookstore, &lt;em&gt;Crossword&lt;/em&gt;. The bookcase is bare now, its shelves empty and cold, its charges packed away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodbye . . . bookcase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You know, we should get stronger boxes, and maybe even sacks to stuff the boxes in,” Daddy’s voice said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Huh? Oh.” I came back from my reminiscences. “Why? And whoever heard of boxes packed inside sacks?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Because the coolies will just throw everything into the luggage compartment, pell-mell, boxes and all — they won’t care what’s in them. You want to make sure your stuff doesn’t get damaged.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How barbaric! I mean, yeah, I got that those poor coolies would be rushed, and that they wouldn’t be lovingly gentle with other people’s belongings, but I couldn’t believe they would actually throw the stuff. I had just opened my mouth to argue, when I had a horrible vision — my beloved books, ripped from their covers (which I had covered again in clear plastic), spilling out of a tattered box on the train station, their spines broken, their pristine, innocent pages mauled by the wet, muddy boots of heartless strangers. It was a vision to douse my soul in dread, and I hastily closed my mouth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yes, of course, let’s get some more boxes! Stronger boxes! Yes — and sacks!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we got stronger boxes, stronger tape, sacks. Resealed everything tightly, especially my fragile books, then tried to stuff the boxes in the sacks, so that even if the boxes were to break due to coolie abuse, the sacks would contain the damage. We had little success with that, and we still had some boxes unsacked, but hey, you can only do so much when you’re pressed for time. Finally, I wrote my name and Delhi address in fat black letters on everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also made up my mind to have a little talk with those coolies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, just like that, it was time to leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodbye . . . Apartment 301-B . . . abode of two years and three months. . . .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Bandra Kurla Station, Bombay&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p style="text-indent: 0"&gt;To the untrained eye of a Martian observer, Bandra station must look no different than an anthill whose residents were unceremoniously roused from their afternoon siesta by a well-aimed stone hurled by an impetuous little rascal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like that indignant anthill, swarming with bewildered, confused ants, the platform was swarming with bewildered, confused people — people hurrying to find their steaming trains; people hurrying to find their steaming relatives; people haggling with hawkers and food vendors; harried mothers yelling at their children to stop goofing off and stay together; young couples helplessly stuck to each other as if with glue, waiting for the train to pull them apart. Occasionally, the nasal voice of the PA system or the rumble of a train enlivened the bustling scene even more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coolies were everywhere, their red jackets announcing their employment as porters working for the Indian Railways. Trundling carts or carrying bags, they wound and weaved expertly among the milling crowd, saviours of the hapless travellers who’d packed too much for their journey. We hired three of their number, two to carry the suitcases and bags, and one to push a cart with the boxes. Hacking a serpentine trail through the forest of people, and tripping over little kids underfoot, we made our way to where the Rajdhani Express was waiting. Bandra to Delhi, 4:14pm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s our train,” I noted, “now where’s the luggage car?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coolies kept on walking, my question too inconsequential to answer, until we reached the last compartment of the train. The luggage car was mostly empty — and to my intense pleasure, the space under the bottommost shelf was perfect to stash the reinforced boxes. We were early, the luggage had not yet started piling up, so there was enough space to stow my stuff safely. It would get wedged in by other people’s things, no chance for anything to get thrown about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Please be careful with these boxes — they have delicate things in them,” I fibbed to the coolies, pointing to the book boxes. They looked at me with mild amusement. “Fragile,” I added weakly, nodding my head, afraid they had not understood. They had. And seen through it too. No delicate, fragile things weigh that much. “Can we put them here? Under this shelf? Please?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coolies must have had pets at home, because they seemed to know that certain kinds of whining meant that the animal’s wishes were too delicate to be ignored. Recognizing the same notes of whining in the words coming out of my mouth, they acquiesced, and my precious books got stowed safely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center"&gt;. . .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;How&lt;/em&gt; much?! You tipped them &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; much?!” Father asked again, eyes widening in incredulity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were back in our compartment, nourishing ourselves with greasy food and lukewarm water from the platform-side food stall. While Father was off gathering said food, I had taken care of tipping the coolies for their services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Fifty rupees,” I repeated, chomping on the deliciously oily samosa soaked in sweet chutney.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“FIFTY RUPEES?!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Each.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Tera dimag kharab ho gaya hai&lt;/em&gt;?!” (“Have you lost your &lt;em&gt;mind&lt;/em&gt;?!”) Father yelped, popping in his seat, incredulity giving way to horror.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never can English deliver the sting of a reprimand from incensed parent to idiot child as sharply as the mother tongue can. I shrank a little. The morsel of samosa meekly slid down my throat, wasted. In 1999, fifty rupees was a lot of money. Three times that was a &lt;em&gt;hundred&lt;/em&gt; and fifty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But they were so helpful.” I bleated. “They stored my books safely. Now they won’t get damaged.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You’re &lt;em&gt;leaving&lt;/em&gt; Bombay today, moving your &lt;em&gt;entire&lt;/em&gt; household, and all you’ve been doing is &lt;em&gt;obsessing&lt;/em&gt; over your books!” Father hissed, italicizing his words frequently for maximum impact. “As if those were the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; things that mattered. You can’t even &lt;em&gt;take&lt;/em&gt; them to the US with you —.” He did restrain himself from adding “you &lt;em&gt;idiot&lt;/em&gt;” to the end of that sentence — but the tone of his voice abided by no such restraint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I bought all those books &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; Bombay,” I said petulantly, which, now that I think about it, was somewhat of a non-sequitur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Father’s retort was startled into silence by the sudden shriek of the train. The &lt;em&gt;Rajdhani&lt;/em&gt; was getting ready to leave. On the platform outside, calls of goodbye became louder. Hands went up in farewell, last minute injunctions became firmer, clingy couples came unglued. Some people started walking alongside the train, getting in on the slowly moving vehicle. Others dawdled until they had to run, and were helped in by those already aboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We settled back for our thirteen hour train ride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Farewell . . . Bombay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;New Delhi Railway Station&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p style="text-indent: 0"&gt;The first I saw of my hometown through the haze of the winter fog was the signboard of the Hazrat Nizamuddin station, named for a 13th century Sufi saint, who’s entombed at the nearby dargah. The Rajdhani continued past, on its way to New Delhi station, just a few kilometres ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presently, with the screech of metal and the hiss of brakes, the train jerked to a stop. Sleepy passengers, frozen into blocks of ice by the biting cold of the morning, but now thawing with the promise of hot chai at home, began seeping out of the train, and the scene from the platform in Bombay played out in reverse. Soon there was a crowd at the luggage car, everyone jostling everyone else for their stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We too started making our way to our belongings, but stopped short, mid-stride. Realization, and a sense of irony, had descended upon us. We realized that our stuff was buried behind — and under — everyone else’s, because — well, because we just had to be early for the train, didn’t we? Just so we could store our stuff before anyone else? Karma had frowned at such rectitude, and now it was time to pay for that overzealous punctuality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would, we decided, do us no good to jump into that crowd of passionate luggage-seekers, and risk an elbow in the stomach or a bruise on the face. Or worse — if it was the other way around. So prudently, we stayed away from the mêlée until the passions were spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the crowd thinned and civility crawled back, we made our way, unbruised and unelbowed, to recover our luggage — only to find the door to the compartment being locked by a triumphant Railways official.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hey, unlock the door!” we howled at the official, “we haven’t got our luggage yet!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He gave us a withering look, born of the carefully cultivated condescension of public servants for the public they serve. “I can’t open the door. The train has to leave.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Leave&lt;/em&gt;? To &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt;?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Old Delhi. That’s where it terminates.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More realization descended upon us — New Delhi was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the train’s final destination. &lt;em&gt;Our&lt;/em&gt; journey might have ended at New Delhi, but the &lt;em&gt;train&lt;/em&gt;’s ended at Old Delhi. And sure enough, even as we watched, helpless, the &lt;em&gt;Rajdhani&lt;/em&gt; started to move, slowly but inexorably, enroute to its tryst with that destiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But our luggage! We have to get our luggage!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The — luggage — will — open — at — Old — Delhi,” he said coldly, supremely indifferent to our predicament. “Go talk to the office.” He waved a dismissive hand in an indeterminate direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dejected, tired and cold, Karma cackling in our ears, we dragged ourselves to the office — but that edifice held no sign of human habitation. The single chair stood forlorn and empty with no indication that it had been occupied recently, the lights were out, and creatures of the night had not yet retired for the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like all self-respecting government employees, this official too was conspicuous only by his absence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the quest of someone else who might help, we saw, by the pale light of the lone bulb outside, a human figure under the stairwell. We made our way there post haste — and discovered the supine body of another Railways employee. This gentleman, even more self-respecting than his absconding colleague, was fast asleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Let’s just go to Old Delhi,” Daddy said with resignation. “The luggage is already there, what will these people here do anyway?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following that impeccable logic, we gathered what little stuff we had and walked out of the station. But instead of going to Old Delhi right away, we went home first, washed off the grime of the travel, scarfed down some food, and so fortified, returned to Old Delhi station for a battle with bureaucrats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Old Delhi Railway Station&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What is the purpose of your visit here, sir?” the policeman who stopped us at the entrance to the platform demanded. The “sir” was merely decorative.
It wasn’t going to be smooth sailing, we already knew, but we hadn’t expected choppy waters this early. I mentally shook my head at my own naïveté.
“We need to pick up our luggage,” Daddy replied, offering him his train ticket to inspect.
“Your ticket says ‘New Delhi’. Why would your luggage be here, at Old Delhi?”
“We couldn’t get it at New Delhi. The train left before we could get it.”
“So you got off at New Delhi, but you let your luggage come here? Why?” he questioned, eyeballs dilating with anticipatory pleasure. The mathematical logic of his brain was plain to see. Only idiots get off at one station and allow their luggage to go to another. Therefore, these people must be idiots. Also, a fool and his money are soon parted. Therefore, I must have them part with some money (of course, of course, only to teach them a lesson). Therefore, there will be more money in my pocket. QED.
I don’t remember the last time Daddy lied, or lied with a straight face, or lied to a policeman. “Officer,” he began, “I’m a Government employee. Here’s my ID card.” He pulled his identification out of his wallet, showing the policeman his picture, titled by the words “GOVERNMENT OF INDIA”, and his designation as a reasonably senior officer of the Central Water Commission. Then came the blatant lie. “We’re picking up Government stuff. You can come check.”
The policeman’s anticipatory expression turned into a pained grimace; he looked like a cat whose human serf had snatched away its bowl of cream just as it was about to give it a slurpy lick.
Few policemen care to mess with Government stuff, and certainly not a two-bit one who cared only about having his large palms greased by harassing hapless travellers. “I see,” he said, “I guess that’s OK then, sir.” This time the “sir” was a little more sincere, and a little more begrudging.
In glaring contrast with the policeman’s, our salutation to the stationmaster was dripping with obsequiousness.
“Sir,” we said with the deference appropriate to a government employee from whom we need a favour, “would you please help us? We’ve lost our luggage.”
Luckily, the stationmaster was in a good mood, and buoyed, undoubtedly, by our deferential manner, also amenable to our request. In a shockingly short period of time, we had our luggage — all of it, unscathed and whole.
On our way out, this time replete with our belongings and two coolies, we passed the same policeman on the lookout for his next harassment target, trying to make up for his loss of some easy money earlier. Feeling sorry for an officer of the law, reduced to supplementing his meagre government income by preying on the very public he had signed up to serve, Daddy, in an impulsive moment of magnanimity, handed the man a twenty rupee note. “For your troubles,” he said. “Get a cup of tea or something to eat.”
The policeman was dumbfounded. No words of gratitude fell from his mouth, but the surprise, the shock and the wonderment on his face were quite enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frankfurt airport&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next noteworthy event is the flight to the US, Lufthansa flight 412 from Indira Gandhi International Airport, New Delhi, to John F. Kennedy International Airport, New York, via Frankfurt, Germany.
The flight itself was unmemorable, because almost as soon as we boarded, I fell asleep (it was 3:00 in the goddamn night). I did not wait to see the bright lights of my hometown turn into pinpoints, like glitter tossed on the dark fabric of night, nor did I wait to hear the standard announcements before takeoff. I only felt the thrust of the aircraft determinedly crushing me into my seat, before the lullaby of the engines’ drone put me right back to sleep.
After seven-ish hours, most of them spent in uncomfortable slumber, we landed in Frankfurt. My next flight was a few hours away, so I sauntered to the next terminal, taking in the sights of this new, alien place.
Presently, I became aware of a faint humming in my ears. Cursory investigation of my surroundings yielded no insight — no hum of conversation, no hum of machinery, no mosquitoes, and certainly no bees. Yet there was that humming in my ears. Other than that, it was all rather quiet.
And in that quietness, the reason for the mysterious humming came to me almost at once.
In all the time they’d spent on Earth, attached to my head, my ears had been awash in noise: loud horns on the road; conversations that carried across rooms — sometimes even across neighbours’ rooms; the barking of stray dogs commingled with the calls of hawkers touting their wares; general chatter. From the sharp tinkling of bicycle bells to the raucous cacophony of loudspeakers bellowing the latest Bollywood songs to felicitate newlyweds at their wedding, my ears had never known the distress of quietness. And so they were protesting. In the absence of sound at this quiet German airport, my ears, long hopped up on the drug of constant background noise, were now having withdrawal symptoms!
Pleased at having solved the mystery of the phantom humming, I walked on, when something else arrested my progress.
The sight I beheld was not unusual, but it filled my heart with surprise, and, I’m ashamed to admit, the glee of schadenfreude (how fitting that this should be a German word that so aptly describes my emotions for the situation at that German airport). The ceiling of the terminal was leaking water. There was water on the floor, and a large bucket had been placed there, with a big plastic sheet rigged up to the leak to direct the water into the bucket.
In Third World India, such things are commonplace and unremarkable — we’re used to, and prepared for, such system failures. I was delighted to see that even the ultra elite, modern West was fallible.
Not all that much different, then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John F. Kennedy Airport, New York&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both the airplane and my heart felt the thud at the same time. The airplane felt it because, well, because it had landed, and my heart because it had finally figured out that This Was It. I was in the USA. India was on the other side of the planet, and I had to restart my life here, as a fully formed adult. I was an immigrant, an alien. Oh, and because, did I have all my papers, or were they just going to send me back to India, a laughingstock for not even being able to carry the proper papers? I had once lost a bag right before entering Bombay airport for a flight to San Francisco — a bag that had contained my passport, three hundred American dollars, a few travellers’ cheques, and some stuff of lesser importance. Horrible memories of that abortive trip and of the embarrassment of having to explain the situation to my surprised (but supportive) colleagues the next day, were making me more than a little nervous.
I double-checked that I had my passport; I glared at the visa, daring it to tell me it was fake; and I triple-checked that I had correctly filled out the Customs Declaration Form that they’d given me on the airplane. It was a simple form with questions about what I was carrying into the USA, but it was my first brush with US officialdom on US soil.
Though innocuous, this form reminded me of the one I’d had to fill when I was applying for my visa. That form was called DS-156, and it had some rather insulting questions, causing me to question the faculties of the author. How, I wonder, is someone expected to answer a question that goes, “Do you intend to engage in terrorist activities while in the United States or have you ever engaged in terrorist activities?” with anything but a “no”? Or, this one: “Have you ever committed, ordered, incited, assisted, or otherwise participated in extrajudicial killings, political killings or other acts of violence?” I had the momentary, mad desire to answer, “I’d tell you, but then I’d have to kill you.” But that momentary, mad desire was extinguished when I read the next question: “Are you coming to the United States to engage in prostitution or unlawful commercialized vice or have you been engaged in prostitution or procuring prostitution within the past 10 years?” Like firecrackers on Diwali, sarcastic responses burst into my brain, each more snarky than the last. “Well, I am going there to make money . . . how much does that pay?” went one. Another went, “Uh, not in the past ten,” but I liked this one the best, “Which specialized skills do you need for that, considering that my H1-B visa is for specialized skills not available in the US?”
Demeaning, insulting questions, products of paranoid minds — and I remember feeling the sharp impulse to abandon my plans of going to a country which a priori assumed people were criminals and scum. Fortunately, wiser counsel had prevailed, and I had answered each of those questions with a safe, unglamorous “no”.
The customs form, however, wasn’t written by someone who was high on something. It just asked what stuff I was carrying with me, how much monetary value it had, and if I was carrying something like plants or fresh fruits that were not allowed. Even so, like a child dreading showing his report card to his parents because he knows he’s messed up his test, I dreaded facing the customs official with my folder of documents and forms.
A pleasant mannered official looked up from his desk behind the little window and asked for my papers. I handed them over, legs trembling. This was it! This was the moment! This was when he would stand up and yell at me for getting the spelling of my name wrong on the form and declare me an impostor. Then he would have me arrested and deported in disgrace.
“First time in the USA?” he asked, unexpectedly polite.
“Y - yes,” I stammered.
“Where will you be going?”
“New Jersey, but I’ll be staying with my brother-in-law in Connecticut for a few days.”
“And where’s your wife?”
“She’s already there.”
“Oh, good.” Then he had me take fingerprints, stamped my passport, and said cordially, “Welcome to America.”
“Thank you, Mr. So-and-So.” (I’m afraid I’ve forgotten his name, so I’m just going to call him Mr. So-and-So.)
“Have a good day.”
“You as well.”
It was done! It was official! I was in the USA! I almost ran to the luggage area before Mr. So-and-So could change his mind. Gathering the two suitcases that contained all my worldly possessions, I opened the exit door and greeted the bright, sunny day with a big smile.
The bright, sunny day greeted me right back with a big slap.
Shards of frigid air ripped into my body, shredding my apology of a winter coat into tiny strips of cloth that hung limply off my flash-frozen bones. My body went taut, tears stung my suddenly dry eyes, and my smile contorted into a blue-lipped rictus of death. Only some parts of my brain remained functional — the part that dimly registered the irony of being skewered by nothing more than air, and the part that was certain my blood had congealed, which is why I wasn’t bleeding despite the thousand cuts in my flesh. It was the day after Christmas, wintertime in the USA, and the temperature was minus 12C, a fact I was rather cavalier about before my journey.
Just as I was about to scuttle back inside the terminal, I saw Upendra and Bhanu coming to receive me. Teeth chattering, legs trembling with the effort of moving against the heavy cold, I stumbled to them, and almost passed out with relief in their warm car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beginning&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ride to Upendra’s house in Ansonia, Connecticut (pronounced Kuh-NET-i-cut, God knows why, not Kuh-NECK-ti-cut, as you’d expect) was quite an experience too. I saw cars driving in proper lanes, with nary a honk. I saw people standing in line for the bus. I saw cars stopped at a STOP sign, even when no one was looking. What were they terrified of, I wondered, to be behaving so nicely?
The military green Toyota Camry (Connecticut licence plate 426 NTH — yes! I still remember the licence plate! Twenty years on!) drove on what I would later learn was Interstate 95, part of a system of highways with no traffic lights. It was also, I was told, an easier than usual drive because most people were on Christmas holiday. For an hour we drove non-stop before taking the exit into Bridgeport, then drove some more on Route 8 until we reached the little town of Ansonia, nestled in the hills and what would be lush greenery during the summer. I was drinking in every sight. I saw fairytale houses, their sloping roofs thick with snow. I saw supermarkets the size of cricket fields. I even saw a cheerful little funeral home, festooned with Christmas decorations, doors agape with sly invitation.
Finally, after about an hour and a half, there we were. I would spend two weeks at Upendra’s before my first job in the USA took me to East Brunswick, New Jersey.
This was the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Memoir"></category><category term="Funny"></category><category term="India"></category><category term="Bombay"></category><category term="USA"></category></entry><entry><title>Oblivion</title><link href="https://al-faaz.github.io/stories/2019/09/05/oblivion" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Al Faaz</name></author><id>tag:al-faaz.github.io,2019-09-05:/stories/2019/09/05/oblivion</id><summary type="html">&lt;p style="text-indent: 0"&gt;She steals up to my side quietly as I sit by the window, watching the evening shadows fade. Stray sounds of life outside come in through the glass, borne on the still, cold air of dusk, but fall, unheard, on my ears, and perish. The clock ticks in the background …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p style="text-indent: 0"&gt;She steals up to my side quietly as I sit by the window, watching the evening shadows fade. Stray sounds of life outside come in through the glass, borne on the still, cold air of dusk, but fall, unheard, on my ears, and perish. The clock ticks in the background somewhere, futilely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unaware of her presence, unmolested in my reverie I sit, for unending time, until the shadows disappear, the sounds dim, and the evening sinks into the night. Her being is more palpable for the darkness, but I only notice her when she encloses me in an embrace that doesn’t let go. At the lightness of her touch, I look up, surprised out of my ruminations. But even her presence cannot stop the flow of thoughts, thoughts of different times, some lost in the past, some lost to the future. So in that darkness we sit, she and I, in companionable silence, sharing that indeterminate space between memory and fantasy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the only sound is the remorseless ticking of the clock, she beckons me to the nearly empty room that lies at the end of the short hallway a few miles away. The only things there are my bed and sundry belongings, which I must have left untended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obeying her unspoken invitation, I follow her to the room. There’s nothing to do there but lie down, and gaze, as I often do, through the lone window into the dark abyss of the sky. The prospect of bed is faintly pleasant, but sleep is elusive. I lay my head in her lap and wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presently, she begins playing with my hair and caressing my brow, her touch soft, and as my eyes start to close, I feel a reluctant peace returning. Her spell is working, and soon I shall have forgotten everything. I wish again that I could stay here forever beside her gossamer form, but I know that won’t happen. She’ll be gone when I wake, leaving me behind to yearn another day. But she’ll come back, she always does, and we’ll do this little dance once more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She’s my truest companion — the Night — and I shall wait for her to return tomorrow, when she’ll bring me her most precious gift again. Oblivion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Poetry"></category><category term="Solitude"></category></entry><entry><title>The Old Timer</title><link href="https://al-faaz.github.io/stories/2019/09/05/the-old-timer" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Al Faaz</name></author><id>tag:al-faaz.github.io,2019-09-05:/stories/2019/09/05/the-old-timer</id><summary type="html">&lt;p style="text-indent: 0"&gt;I still remember the day I came into this family. It promised to be a good time &amp;mdash; and it was. There was never a dull moment with me around. Guy and Gal loved me. I was their companion when they came home, weary from work everyday. I was there when …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p style="text-indent: 0"&gt;I still remember the day I came into this family. It promised to be a good time &amp;mdash; and it was. There was never a dull moment with me around. Guy and Gal loved me. I was their companion when they came home, weary from work everyday. I was there when they had their fights. I kept Gal company when Guy went away for almost two years, returning only on weekends, and Gal came back to an empty home everyday &amp;mdash; except for me. I made her evenings cheerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen strangers become friends, houses moved, love and laughter, fights and make-ups, and all the ups and downs of a full life. I have even seen two beautiful, wide-eyed children come into the family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I have grown old now. It's been twelve years since that first day in the family, and I am hearing talk about replacing me, getting a newer one of my kind. It's kind of scary, but I suppose everyone wants more verve, more youth, more life. I don’t begrudge Guy and Gal for wanting more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have to admit, if I am honest with myself, that these youngsters do have a lot going for them. They can do things I could never do, even in my prime. They are bolder, smarter, classier than I ever was when I was younger. In time, I hope, they'll learn humility too, as age catches up with them, just as it has caught up with me. But despite my age, I’m still good for more. I can still light up a room, still give people the companionship they need. I am still bright and cheerful and agile, and I don't bother anyone. I've never even had health problems, such as that plague many of my age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, it isn't time for me to die &amp;mdash; but that's what will happen if they just give me away. No one believes I can be of any use any more because I am too old &amp;mdash; they just want the youngest and the most attractive ones. Youth and beauty are so seductive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guy and Gal understand. I can see it in their faces, hear it in their voices &amp;mdash; they are hesitant to just give me away &amp;mdash; they know I'll only be put to sleep. Surely the end must come one day, but for now, while I still have some good life remaining in me, I hope they find a good home to put me in &amp;mdash; there must be someone out there who will be happy for the company, but can't afford one like me otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I am not sure, and I’ll admit to being a little scared too. No one seems to like an old, boxy TV any more.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Memoir"></category></entry></feed>